All
right, בוקר טוב. Boker Tov.
So today's דף daf is מ"ה. Mem Heh. We pick up at
the very, very bottom of מ"ד עמוד ב'. Mem Dalet Amud Bet.
We are talking about again taking the לולב lulav in the בית
המקדש, Beis HaMikdash, and also the ערבה, aravah, which is a theme
that we're going to continue. But we first finish up the taking
of the לולב lulav in the בית המקדש Beis HaMikdash and bringing
it ערב שבת. Erev Shabbos. So the משנה Mishnah says that they
would bring it ערב שבת Erev Shabbos and that they would be
arranged by the אצטבא, itztaba, which was some type of a square,
of a covered plaza was the word
I was going for,
but like a public space, but apparently had rows of chairs in
it as well. So the גמרא Gemara says like
this: תני תנא קמיה דרב נחמן, Tani tana kamei d'Rav Nachman, סודרין
אגג האצטבא. sodrin agag ha'itztaba. You would put the לולבים lulavs on
the roof of the אצטבא. itztaba. אמר ליה, Amar lei, דכי ויבשו
הוא צריך? d'chi v'yavshan hu tzarich? Are you doing it to dry
them out? Why do you put them on the roof? It's going
to be exposed to the sun and they'll get dried out. אלא
אימא אגף האצטבא, Ela eima agaf ha'itztaba, on the top of it,
not on the roof, but presumably the top of the chairs or
the benches. אמר רחבה אמר רב יהודה, Amar Rechava amar Rav Yehuda,
הר הבית Har HaBayis כפול היה, kaful hayah, סטיו לפנים מסטיו. stav
lifnim mistav. The הר הבית Har HaBayis was a double סטיו stav
or stoa, I think you would say, which is like rows of
columns. They have a picture there? Yeah? Yeah. So okay, so yeah,
I mean, actually, if you think about the Cardo, right, in ירושלים,
Yerushalayim, Cardo, right, you know you have those like double columns and
you have you know you have like the shops or whatever. So
that's he's describing the way that it looked and that wasn't, you
know, that was on the הר הבית Har HaBayis itself and presumably
in that area is where they stored these לולבים. lulavim. Fine. We
now look to the next משנה. Mishnah. So the initial discussion had
been right that the taking of the לולב lulav would override or
would be done on שבת, Shabbos, it wouldn't override an actual biblical
violation, but it was done on שבת Shabbos on the first day
and ערבה aravah on the last day, although ערבה aravah is really
only a biblical מצוה mitzvah according to the idea that it's biblical,
you know, it's not in the verses explicitly, but it's a הלכה
למשה מסיני halacha leMoshe miSinai or whatever. Anyway, it's only in the
מקדש, Mikdash, and we therefore have some, we have retained, and therefore
for it, the seventh day, הושענא רבה, Hoshana Rabbah, would be the
day it would be done on שבת, Shabbos, and we've retained the
practice out of the מקדש Mikdash to do it on הושענא רבה
Hoshana Rabbah as well, which the גמרא Gemara has attributed to מנהג
נביאים minhag nevi'im or יסוד נביאים. yesod nevi'im. So now we actually
look at the משנה Mishnah that describes exactly what was done in
the מקדש. Mikdash. We looked at this earlier, now we're going to
look at it inside.
מצות ערבה כיצד? Mitzvas aravah keitzad? What was the מצוה mitzvah of
the ערבה? aravah? מקום היה למטה מירושלים, Makom hayah lemata miYerushalayim, there
was a place below ירושלים, Yerushalayim, ושמו מוצא, u'shmo Motza, the name
of this village or whatever was called Motza. יורדין לשם, Yordin l'sham,
they would go down there, ומלקטים משם מורביות של ערבה, u'melaktim misham
murbiyot shel aravah, they would gather from there like these big branches
of ערבות, aravahs, ובאין וזוקפין אותם לצידי המזבח, u'va'in v'zokfin osam l'tzidei
hamizbe'ach, and they would put it and they take it and they
sort of stick it in around the מזבח, mizbe'ach, by the edges
of the מזבח. mizbe'ach. וראשיהם
כפופים על גבי המזבח, V'rosheihem kefufim agab hamizbe'ach, and as we discussed
the other day, they would sort of like be bending over, a
canopy over the tops over the מזבח. mizbe'ach.
Yeah, well we're going to discuss that in a minute. תקעו והריעו
ותקעו. Take'u v'heri'u v'take'u. So they did תקיעה תרועה תקיעה tekiah teruah
tekiah when they stuck it in, like, you know, that would be
part of the whole ritual way of also rejoicing. We're going to
see when we get to the whole discussion about the water drawing
ceremony and the ניסוך המים, nisuch hamayim, they would do תקיעה תרועה
תקיעה, tekiah teruah tekiah, so here too it would be another ritual
that they would do around the מזבח, mizbe'ach, for also connected obviously
to water, ערבי נחל arvei nachal and, you know, how much this
grows on water, with a
תקיעה תרועה תקיעה. tekiah teruah tekiah. בכל יום מקיפין את המזבח פעם
אחת. Bechol yom makifin es hamizbe'ach pa'am achas. Every day during סוכות
Sukkos when they would do this ערבה aravah ritual, they would walk
around the מזבח mizbe'ach once,
ואומרים v'omrim and they'd say, אנא ה' הושיעה נא, Ana Hashem hoshia
na, אנא ה' הצליחה נא. Ana Hashem hatzlicha na. Please God save
us, please God make us successful, and that also, not coincidentally, is
where we do the shaking of the לולב. lulav. I'll also remind
you that according to one opinion earlier in the גמרא, Gemara, this
marching around the מזבח mizbe'ach was not with the ערבה, aravah, but
was with the whole לולב, lulav, right? And if you think about
it, right, that's what we do. We do the הקפות hakafos with
the whole לולב, lulav, right? We do the אנא ה' הושיעה נא
Ana Hashem hoshia na part refrain when we are doing the הקפות,
hakafos, and it ties into the fact that when we take the
לולב, lulav, we shake the לולב lulav at the אנא ה' הושיעה
נא. Ana Hashem hoshia na. So it all sort of ties in
together. Now what's the significance of doing it at אנא ה' הושיעה
נא? Ana Hashem hoshia na? Obviously it's an aspect of prayer and,
you know, again, the rainy season is coming up, you want it
to be raining and so on. It's worth also noting... It's worth
also noting that תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* points out that based on the
פסוק pasuk *pasuk* in דברי הימים *Divrei Hayamim* where it says אז
ירננו עצי היער az yeranenu atzei haya'ar. *az yerannenu atzei haya'ar*, you
know the trees of the forest will burst out in song and
they'll say הושיענו אלוהי ישענו *hoshienu Elohei yishenu*, save us God of
our salvation. So this is connected to this also idea of שירה
*shirah* and song and שמחה Simcha *simcha*, so it's also a sense
of thanking God for the past, which is you know also very
much a sense of the שמחה Simcha, *simcha* of סוכות Sukkot, *Sukkot*
and the use of these agricultural products. Okay, so you have that,
so you have that connection with the shaking of the לולב Lulav
*lulav* at the אנא Ana, ה' הושיעה נא *ana Hashem hoshia na*
and you now have it also with this ritual on the altar
which might have been with the לולב Lulav *lulav*, might have been
with the ערבה Arava. *aravah* with the אנא Ana, ה' הושיעה נא
*ana Hashem hoshia na*. רבי יהודה אומר *Rabbi Yehuda omer*, now רבי
יהודה *Rabbi Yehuda* says you say אני והו הושיעה נא Ani V'hu
Hoshia Na. *ani vahu hoshia na*, I and he save us. Now
that is a very challenging word, what does that mean? So you
know I'm going to go back and unpack that in a minute,
let's finish reading the משנה Mishnah *Mishnah*. Okay, ואותו היום *v'oto hayom*,
so that's what you would do on the normal day of the
week, but that day meaning day seven, the big day, מקיפין את
המזבח שבע פעמים *makifin et hamizbeach sheva peamim*, you would do it
seven times. And of course this is also evocative of יריחו *Yericho*,
you know marching around each day and then finally doing a seven
times marching and then the walls fell down. So what exactly that's
supposed to be evoking, you know hopefully not that the walls of
the מזבח Mizbe'ach *mizbeach* fall down, maybe the walls between us and
God will fall down thinking about it that way, but also the
sense of salvation, you know the sense about sort of saving us
from distress and you know being there at the time of when
we need you seems to be being evoked also in terms of
the whole thing that was done at יריחו *Yericho*. בשעת פטירתן מה
היו אומרים *beshat petiratan mah hayu omrim*, what would they say when
they would take leave of the altar? So it's quite fascinating that
whole idea of taking leave of, you know you normally don't ask
after the כהנים *kohanim* finished their daily service you know in the
in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash* what do they do
to take leave but here they would have a ritual of taking
leave. So what would they say? יופי לך מזבח Lach Mizbeach. יופי
לך l'ka, מזבח mizbe'ach, *yofi lach mizbeach yofi lach mizbeach*, beauty is
to you oh altar, beauty is to you oh altar. רבי אליעזר
אומר *Rabbi Eliezer omer*, רבי אליעזר *Rabbi Eliezer* would say they said
לקי ולך v'lach מזבח mizbe'ach *l'Ko v'lach mizbeach*, to God and to
you oh altar, לקי ולך מזבח mizbe'ach. *l'Ko v'lach mizbeach*, to God
and to you oh altar, which is very interesting. כמעשהו בחול Kemaasehu
Vachol, כך מעשהו בשבת *k'maasehu bechol kach maasehu beShabbat*, like they would
do in the weekday they would do on שבת Shabbos *Shabbat*. אלא
שהיו מלקטין אותן מערב *ela shehayu malketin otan me'erev*, but here's what
they would do because by שבת *Shabbat* we know you had to
prepare ahead of time. So the actual
walking around seven times and the sticking in that they would do
because that we said is done on הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba, *Hoshanah
Rabbah* on שבת *Shabbat* in the מקדש Mikdash *Mikdash*. But the preparation
they would do ahead of time. So what would they do? היו
מלקטין אותן מערב *hayu malketin otan me'erev*, they would gather up these
ערבה Arava *aravah* branches from while it was still Friday. ומניחין אותן
בגיגיות של זהב *umanichin otan begigiyot shel zahav*, and they would put
it in golden barrels מערב כדי שלא יכמושו *me'erev k'dei shelo yichmoshu*
so it should not wilt. רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says they'd be water
in the barrel. I don't know if the interaction of gold and
water and the chemical interaction of that's good or bad for preserving
them. Gold doesn't interact.
Oh so it's not.
Gold is pretty inert.
Okay so there you go. It doesn't rust. All right.
רבי יוחנן בן
ברוקה אומר *Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka omer*, חריות של דקל היו מביאין
*chariyot shel dekel hayu mevi'in*, that they would actually bring big sticks
of a palm tree וחובטין אותן בקרקע בצידי המזבח *vechovtin otan bakarka
betzidei hamizbeach* and and those they would put on the ground near
the altar. Now again what does the word חובט *chovet* mean? And
before רש"י Rashi *Rashi* said that the word חובט *chovet* like חיבוט
ערבה Arava *chibbut aravah* which was a description of what we would
do, רש"י Rashi *Rashi* says it means like to to shake it.
But here וחובטין אותן בקרקע *v'chovtin otan bakarka* seems much more like
it means that they would like bang it against the ground or
they would maybe insert it into the ground. And that's as David
pointed out yesterday you know the רמב"ם *Rambam* says that as well
by the earlier discussion about the חיבוט ערבה arava *chibbut aravah* which
was our because we you know that is part of our practice
is to hit it against the ground. So here you have that
word וחובטין בקרקע *v'chovtin bakarka* בצידי המזבח *betzidei hamizbeach*. ואותו היום נקרא
חיבוט חריות Chibut Chariyot, *v'oto hayom nikra chibbut chariyot*. That day was
called the banging or the or the or the sticking in of
the sticks of the palm tree. Okay now תוספות Tosafos *Tosafot* raises
a question, first of all would he say that you would do
this just on הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba *Hoshanah Rabbah* or did he
say that you did this every day? Not so clear. He said
אותו היום *oto hayom*, that day, so maybe it's what he says
you did הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba, *Hoshanah Rabbah*. תוספות Tosafos, *Tosafot* also
asks did he deny that you had an ערבה arava *aravah* ritual
or was he just saying that this was in addition to the
ערבה arava. *aravah* ritual, right? Also not clear. But again something that
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* is sort of saying is like הלכה למשה
מסיני *halacha l'Moshe miSinai* or biblical, it's quite fascinating that there's this
ambiguity around it. So that's why you know it might be easier
to understand that he's not denying the basic ערבה arava *aravah* ritual
he's saying that they would also do this but it seems like
he's giving primacy to this, right? It wasn't this day wasn't called
שביעי של ערבה arava *shevi'i shel aravah*. This day was called יום
חיבוט, what is it called,
חיבוט חריות, the palm branch banking or the palm branch insertion. And
again by the way notice it raises of the same issue, the
ambiguity that the גמרא Gemara raised about whether when they did the
daily procession, not on הושענא רבה, Hoshana Rabba, did they do that
with a לולב Lulav or did they do it with an ערבה.
So clearly they're doing these rituals around the altar with either ערבה
or לולב Lulav or both,
and obviously it very much seems to be very much connected to
the whole water ideas. Charlie pointed out palms need an enormous amount
of water as well, so all of these are evocative of this
whole water. And of course today as well, we do our הושענות
Hoshanas with the לולב Lulav and then the last day we do
specifically with the ערבה and the אנא השם הושיעה נא Ana Hashem
Hoshia Na sort of
connects the shaking of the לולב Lulav and what was done here.
Okay then, the last line is a little unrelated. מיד, Miyad, immediately,
תינוקות שומטין את לולביהן, Tinokos Shomtin Es Lulaveihen, meaning presumably immediately on
הושענא רבה Hoshana Rabba. or now we're done. We've done all of
the rituals. Like that's how you sort of feel, like you've gone
through such a
busy סוכות, Sukkot finally it's הושענא רבה, Hoshana Rabba. then you do
like two hours, three hours in שול Shul for הושענא רבה, Hoshana
Rabba, finally you're done with the whole thing. So now what do
you do with your לולב lulav and אתרוג? Esrog? You know normally
there's a place in the שול Shul afterwards where you can put
them to dispose of them. So that's what the משנה Mishnah says.
You're finally done, it's הושענא רבה. Hoshana Rabbah. So at least the
תינוקות ביום טוב Tinokos B'Yomtov שומטין את לולביהן Shomtin Es Lulaveihen would
sort of like the way תוספות Tosafos reads it is throw down
their לולבים Lulavs ואוכלין אתרוגיהן V'ochlin Esrogeihen and they'd eat their אתרוגים.
Esrogs. Good, we're done. So they would get rid of their לולבים
Lulavs and they'd eat their אתרוגים. Esrogs. רש"י Rashi reads it מיד
תינוקות, Miyad Tinokos, from the hands of the kids, שומטין את לולביהן,
Shomtin Es Lulaveihen, the adults would take the לולבים Lulavs out of
the hands of the kids ואוכלין אתרוגיהן V'ochlin Esrogeihen and eat the
אתרוגים Esrogs from the kids. So רש"י Rashi actually says that this
was, so you know that this was the adults taking it like
taking candy from a baby by taking לולב lulav and an אתרוג
Esrog from a baby. Anyway, so רש"י Rashi says it wasn't just
that they were saying oh finally we're done we can eat our
אתרוגים, Esrogs, but there was some type of a שמחה Simcha
associated
with the end of הושענא hoshana רבה. If you look at the
last רש"י Rashi on the משנה mishna, here he says אוכלין אתרוגיהן,
Ochlin Esrogeihen, רש"י Rashi says של תינוקות, Shel Tinokos, ואין בו דבר
משום גזל ולא משום דרכי שלום, V'ein Bo Davar Mishum Gezel V'lo
Mishum Darchei Shalom, it's not inappropriate though you're stealing it from the
kids, שכך נהגו מחמת
שמחה. Shekach Nahagu Machmas Simcha. That was the practice because of joy,
which is interesting because it gets us to
the theme of שמחה, Simcha which again is always a סוכות Sukkot,
theme, but a theme of שמחה at the culmination of סוכות, Sukkot
which is interesting in terms of origins of the whole idea of
שמחת תורה. Simchas Torah. Where does this whole sense about that the
culmination of סוכות Sukkot. after שמיני עצרת Shemini Atzeres is this whole
day focused on שמחה and שמחת תורה? Simchas Torah? And it's actually
quite interesting because actually we just finished פורים Purim and there are
a couple of הלכות Halachas that relate both to פורים Purim and
שמחת תורה Simchas Torah that when people are doing certain things מחמת
שמחה, Machmas Simcha, there's like an assumption of מחילה. Mechila. Like you
know, a, first of all there's a famous רמ"א Rama that says
that if you're dressing up and men are cross-dressing as women, that
it's not a problem of בגד אשה Beged Isha because it's all
done sort of מחמת שמחה, Machmas Simcha, which is fascinating because that's
like a biblical prohibition and to explain that contextually. But also they
speak about things that you would do like you would do jousts
or you would do juggling
and you'd do other types of things that then could ultimately damage
somebody's property. You also find this sometimes around weddings and an idea
like oh it's all done מחמת שמחה Machmas Simcha and there's a
presumed מחילה Mechila and so on. So that's what רש"י Rashi is
reading in here and again it is interesting thinking about this as
the culmination and how that ultimately in our practice culminates in שמחת
תורה. Simchas Torah. Okay, but anyway that's the last line, but going
back earlier the interesting thing
that is that we didn't really unpack here was the first of
all the taking leave of the altar and what's that about? But
again it really in a way raises the question about the focus
around the altar
and it is worth thinking about how central, how many sacrifices were
brought on סוכות. Sukkot. There would be like the 70 cows and
the 14 sheep, every day was 14 sheep, I mean enormous the
amount of sacrifices on סוכות. Sukkos, So there is this highly
altar-centered period of that חג. Chag. So if you're thinking that sort
of it's an issue about taking leave, right on the seventh day
on הושענא רבה, so basically like we've been overusing the מזבח during
this
week and there were all the rituals on the altar, there was
the pouring of the water on the altar, there was the שמחת
בית השואבה, Simchas Beis Hasho'eiva, so it's like now we're actually getting
back to our normal year, we're sort of there is this aspect
of like taking leave from the altar during that time. So but
that's fascinating to note just that phenomenon. The other thing about אני
והו הושיעה נא. Ani Vahu Hoshiana What does that mean? So that's
very strange. So רש״י Rashi points out the גמרא Gemara doesn't unpack
what it means, but רש״י Rashi points out if you think about
אנא השם, Ana Hashem, right? אנא השם הושיעה נא. Ana Hashem hoshia
na. So השם Hashem when you have אני והו, Ani Vahu, right?
אני והו, Ani Vahu, wait that's the והו, Vahu, whoops I just
wrote God's name. Oh my God.
Can you erase it?
Write this black. That was tough.
I wanted to... okay, we're going to have to get back to
that. I don't know what I'm going to do about that. Okay
anyway, boy. Okay, you have והו Vahu here, so which is... so
the... now that I have God's name up on the board,
so you have, you know, the גימטריא gematria here is eleven
and six is seventeen, right? That's the והו? Vahu? Oh no wait,
it's without the אלף. Aleph. Okay, it's eleven, it's...
it's sixteen, right? But then you have the extra יוד, Yud, right?
Did I do this right?
12,
17... we have the יוד, Yud, right? Which... so and this is
אנא, which is the... the one and God's name is 26. That's
27. We just with the יוד Yud plus the 17 is 27.
So it's the same גימטריא, gematria, right? יוד-קא-ואו-קא Yud-Kei-Vav-Kei is 26, right?
10, 26. So אנא, take out the אלף-נון, Aleph-Nun, the 26 and
one is 27. Take out the אלף-נון, Aleph-Nun, the יוד Yud and
the והו Vahu is 27. So רש״י Rashi points out that it's
the same גימטריא. gematria. Okay, it's very nice that it's the same
גימטריא, gematria, but it doesn't exactly explain why you would do it.
So רש״י Rashi has another פשט pshat that based on a whole
thing that there's three פסוקים pesukim around the פסוק of בשלח Beshalach
where it says
ויסע מלאך האלקים ויבא בין מחנה מצרים ויבא Vayisa malach Elokim vayavo
bein machne Mitzrayim vayavo etc. etc. etc. those three פסוקים. pesukim. רש״י
Rashi says each one of those פסוקים pesukim has 72 letters, 72
letters in them, which is one of God's like you know hidden
names. And that if you do a various way of combining the
different letters of the פסוקים, pesukim, I'm not going to bother you
with it, you're going to get to ways that you can spell
out the אני והו. Ani Vahu. Okay, that's all very lovely. What
does it have to do with anything? So תוספות Tosafos says an
idea, if you look at תוספות אני והו, Tosafos Ani Vahu, look
at the תוספות, Tosafos it says
the גימטריא gematria אנא השם, Ana Hashem, and then he quotes the
whole רש״י Rashi about how to recombine letters and get it, and
then in the middle of תוספות Tosafos it says עדיין צריך טעם
לזה למה נשתנו שני שמות הללו, Adayin tzarich taam la-zeh lamma nishtanu
shenei shemos halalu, why these two,
you know, what is it about these two words? דאמרינן להו טפי
מאחריני, De-amrinan lehu t'fei me-achrini, and if there's other ways of combining,
you know, these letters and getting other sort of three-letter combinations drawn
from שם השם, Shem Hashem, why do we say אני והו? Ani
Vahu? So he says משום דדרשינן באיכה רבתי קרא דכתיב ביחזקאל ואני
בתוך הגולה, Mishum de-darshinan be-Eichah Rabbati kera de-chsiv b'Yechezkel v'Ani b'soch hagolah,
I am... was amongst in the exile, דקרא דכתיב בירמיה והוא אסור
בזיקים, de-kra de-chsiv b'Yirmiyah v'hu asur bazikim, He meaning God was bound
in chains as it were, כביכול ki-vyachol הוא בעצמו, hu b'atzmo, like
God Himself is trapped in the exile with us. והיינו הושענא שיושיע
את עצמו. V'hainu hoshana she-yoshia es atzmo. So what תוספות is saying
is, and this is a very radical kabbalistic idea, you know that
God is in exile with us, and that God sort of when
we come out of exile, God is also redeeming God's self out
of exile. So אני והו Ani Vahu meaning אני ani בני ישראל
Bnei Yisrael like ואני בתוך הגולה ani b'soch hagolah והוא v'Hu and
God, הושענא like God should save both of us, God should save
me and God should save God, and God should redeem us all,
you know, redeem God's self from exile together with redeeming me. Which
is an idea that we actually do say in the הושענות, Hoshanos,
right? If you think at the end of the הושענות Hoshanos where
we say where it says והוצאתי
אתכם v'hotzeisi eschem now could be punctuated והוצאתי אתכם, v'hotzeisi it'chem, I
will go out with you, you know, not just I will take
you out and redeem you, but I will redeem myself with you.
So this is obviously a pretty darn radical, you know, and powerful
kabbalistic idea that we sort of, you know, our fate and God's
fate are tied up together. So that's what תוספות says that this
idea of save us, you know, is also God save God's self,
and of course the funny thing is that why was this so
relevant, you know, it's one thing for us to say it now
post-exile, we're saying what they did at the time of the בית
המקדש Beis HaMikdash where they weren't in exile, so what's that, you
know, so why exactly that would be the relevant idea at that
time is not, you know, is not so clear, but that definitely
is a theme that's going on here and that plays out in
some of the liturgy that we say around הושענא רבה. Some
people feel that this is real כפירה kfira and they The whole
question of do you pronounce it אני והו, Ani Vehu, which is
he being God, or do you pronounce it אני והו, Ani Veho,
which is
like not a meaningful word, but it's a way of sort of
saying whatever it means, it's some
more esoteric meaning, but we're not actually saying you God, והו. Vehu.
So there's a whole question about what your different סידורים Siddurim you'll
see different things in terms of that.
Let's see what this
says. אני והו Ani Veho this has. So it doesn't have any
discussion. I don't know what Artscroll has. Does it have והו Veho
or
והו? Vehu? They have והו? Veho? Do we have an Artscroll? We
do
have an Artscroll there.
The Artscroll has אני והו. Ani Veho. There you go. So a
מחלוקת machlokeit Artscroll and
Koren.
Let's see if they have any comment here in the notes.
It has an asterisk.
אני והו Ani Veho is the English translation of this. Oh,
here. All right.
Identified by Rashi in סוכה Sukka as two in a series of
seventy-two divine names, blah blah blah. In the mystical formulation, okay, wonderful.
The particular gematria of the two names from the גמטריא gematria of
אנא השם. Ana Hashem. Just absolutely nothing about why they punctuated it
as והו Veho rather than והו. Vehu. But part of that has
to do with the boldness of this kabbalistic idea. All right, let's
take a look now as we continue. תנו רבנן, Tanu Rabbanan, we
taught in a ברייתא. braita. מקום קלניה הוה. Makom Kalanya Hava. This
place called מוצא Motza where they would get the ערבה branches was
actually a place called קלניה. Kalanya. Now Rashi says that even קלניה
Kalanya is not a proper name, but קלניה Kalanya is an Aramaic
word which means to be free, not enslaved.
התנא דידן מאי טעמא קרי ליה מוצא? Ha-tanna didan mai ta'ama karei
lei Motza? Why was it called
מוצא? Motza? איידי דמיפק מכרגא דמלכא, Aidi demipik mikarga demalka, because it
was free from having to pay the king's tax, קרי ליה מוצא,
karei lei Motza,
it was מוצא, Motza, which means exempted. So actually both the word
קלניה Kalanya and מוצא Motza mean the same thing: free and exempted
from the king's tax. Why exactly, it's not clear. All right. וזוקפין
אותן בצידי המזבח. Vezokfin otan betzidei hamizbe'ach. They put it by the
side of the altar. תנא, Tana, we taught in a ברייתא. braita.
רבות וארוכות, Rabot va-arukot, the ערבה branches were very many and they
were very long, וגבוהות אחת עשרה אמה, vigvohot achas esrei ama, and
it was eleven אמות amot tall, כדי שיהו גוחכות על המזבח אמה,
kedei she-yehu gochachot al hamizbe'ach ama,
that they should be over-arching like leaning over the altar an אמה.
ama. So how did this work? אמר מריימר משום מר זוטרא. Amar
Mareimar mishum Mar Zutra. מריימר Mareimar said in the name of מר
זוטרא. Mar Zutra. שמע מינה, Shema mina, we can infer from this,
אליסוד מנחי להו, al yesod manchi lehu, they would not be on
the ground, they would actually be on the base of the מזבח,
the bottom of them. How do you know? דאי סלקא דעתך ארעא
מנחי להו, De-i salka dachach ara manchi lehu, if it was on
the ground, מכדי, michdi, let's take a look. עלה אמה וכנס אמה
זהו יסוד. Ala ama ve-chanas ama zehu yesod. Here's a ברייתא, braita,
a משנה, excuse me, that describes how the מזבח would look. You
go up an אמה ama and in an אמה, ama, that would
be the base. עלה חמש וכנס אמה זהו סובב. Ala chamesh ve-chanas
ama zehu sovev. You go up five אמות, amot, you go in
an אמה, ama, that's the סובב, sovev, that's the walk-around. עלה שלש
זהו מקום הקרנות. Ala shalosh zehu makom hakranot.
You go up three and then you'd have the place for the
corners. So what does that mean?
It means that here's how it would look.
As I said before, there were thirty-two אמות amot at the base.
So the base would be one אמה ama and then you'd go
in an אמה. ama. Then you'd go up five, and then in
an אמה. ama. And then you'd go up three, that would get
you to the top of the מזבח. Up three and then you'd
have the corners here. Okay. So
basically,
this is what it would look like. So you'd have the base
and down here would be thirty-two wide, but that's not relevant to
us. Okay. And how high would it be? One plus five plus
three would be nine אמות amot plus the extra corner would get
you to ten אמות amot including the corner. Okay. And as you're
going in, it goes in an אמה ama here and in an
אמה ama there. So if you were going to put it at
the base at the foot, and it would have to obviously get
at a bit of an angle, you put it at the foot
and it would be going over and leaning over. So it didn't
really have to, this is a side view, it didn't really have
to lean over the corner, it was leaning over the top. You
understand? If it's in the middle, it
doesn't have to lean over the corner. So how tall does it
have to be? So what did it say? It said how long
were they? It said they were eleven אמות, amot, it said eleven
אמות. amot. Let's figure it out. First of all, it's going to
have to be a little bit longer because of the angle, but
it's not a huge angle. But anyway, up to the top is
going to... Right, you understand if it's in the middle, it doesn't
have to lean over the corner. So how tall do these have
to be? So what did it say? It said how long were
they? It said they were eleven אמות, amot, right? It says eleven
אמות. amot. So let's figure it out. First of all, it's going
to have to be a little bit longer because of the angle.
But it's not a huge angle. But anyway, up to the top
is going to be nine, right? Nine אמות, amot, yes. Now if
it says גוחת אמה, gochot amah, the way רש״י Rashi understands what
that means is that the overhang here, this is the top view
of it, here's the top of the altar, and the overhang is
the actual bend over is an אמה, amah, and it has to
be at least an אמה amah off of the top, otherwise it
would be called like dragging, okay on the top. So רש״י Rashi
understands the גמרא's Gemara assumption is that the bend has to
be an אמה, amah, and it has to be suspended an אמה.
amah. Okay, so if it's nine אמות amot here and the height
is nine and it starts on the floor, okay, so you get
nine, so nine actually nine point
whatever plus an epsilon, 9.2, 9.2, I know, I actually did the
math before, okay, plus an אמה amah plus an אמה, amah, it
has to be bigger, it has to be bigger
than eleven אמות amot because of the angle, if it starts on
the floor it has to be bigger than eleven אמות amot to
hang over, to bend an אמה amah and hang an אמה, amah,
right because of the angle. So the גמרא Gemara says it can't
be that it was on the floor and it was only eleven
אמות. amot. It would have to be that they put it on
the base. And that allowed it to be, now of course the
problem with that is
that how does it get supported on the base? I mean how
does it get supported on the floor? It's all tiled, there's no
ground to stick it in. So presumably wherever you did it they
must have had I don't know like you have like flagpoles, they
must have had some kind of a
stand to put it in.
And that's actually the, they have a picture with a stand? Yeah,
so whether it's on the floor or on the base, it's on
something hard, right? It's not on soft dirt.
They have a separate stand that's not on the base in the
picture.
Right, but so where was it, but anyway where was it? Was
it stood here? Was it stood here? So the גמרא Gemara says
it had to have been on the יסוד, yesod, not on the
floor. Okay, so it says okay שמע מינה. shema mina. So that's
a good proof. So אמר רבי אבהו מאי קרא, Amar Rabbi Abahu
mai kra, where's the verse that you see that the, that we
should have these ערבות aravos going suspended over the altar, hanging up
over the altar? נאמר Ne'emar the verse says אסרו חג בעבותים עד
קרנות המזבח, isru chag ba'avotim ad karnot hamizbe'ach,
which normally is read bind the חג chag the
sacrifice the you know the festival sacrifice with ropes by the horns
of the altar, but here it's being read that רש״י Rashi says
that the word עבותים avotim
can mean trees and the word אסרו isru can mean surround. So
surround you know on the holiday with trees around the corners of
the altar. So that gives you this idea of putting the ערבות
aravos and having them surrounding the altar. Again also notice the emphasis
of trees like תוספות quoted the verse about אז ירננו עצי היער.
אמר רבי אבהו אמר רבי אלעזר, Amar Rabbi Abahu Amar Rabbi Elazar,
now we have a nice little דרשה drasha of this.
כל הנוטל לולב באגודו, Kol hanotel lulav be'igudo, anybody who takes the
לולב lulav in the אגד agged because that's what אסרו חג isru
chag to bind up. So you're binding the לולב lulav with the
הדס hadas and the
ערבה. והדס בעבותו, Ve'hadas ba'avoto, and the הדס hadas which is right
which is עבות, avos, ענף עץ עבות, anaf etz avos, so that's
בעבותים, ba'avotim, you see the play on the words. So אסרו חג
isru chag is סוכות, Sukkos. that's the classic חג. chag. אסרו Isru
bind up, bind up the לולב lulav בעבותו ba'avoto with the הדס
hadas that is an ענף עץ עבות anaf etz avos עד קרנות
המזבח. ad karnot hamizbe'ach.
So if you bind up your לולב lulav and you have your
הדס hadas and you have it all done, then מעלה עליו הכתוב
ma'aleh alav hakatuv the Torah treats it כאילו בנה מזבח ke'ilu bana
mizbe'ach like you built an altar והקריב עליו קרבן ve'hikriv alav korban
and you offered a sacrifice on it, שנאמר she'ne'emar as the verse
says אסרו חג בעבותים isru chag ba'avotim bind up your on the
חג chag with your you know with your עבות avos with your
הדס hadas עד קרנות המזבח ad karnot hamizbe'ach onto the altar. Now
that's very nice because that ties into a theme that we discussed
earlier which is you know the whole idea of the shaking of
the לולב lulav and the waving of the שתי הלחם shtei halechem
we mentioned right, and the connections to the altar, the connections to
where the לולב lulav, is compared to a קרבן korban if you
remember, the אתרוג esrog is compared to a קרבן korban בעלי מומין
baleimum תמימים, temimim, the לולב lulav the whole idea of גזול, gazul,
the waving of it like you would wave the שתי הלחם. shtei
halechem. And here we're getting again that idea you bind it up
and you offer it up to God like you offer up a
sacrifice and that connection. מהרש״א The Maharsha takes this further and he
actually says it doesn't just say you offered a sacrifice, it says
you built the altar because there's the preparation, so the binding of
it together is like the act of construction. You construct the לולב,
lulav you build the altar and then you offer it. And I
think the idea of building an altar particularly resonates because we're talking
about a post-מקדש Mikdash reality. There is no altar to offer things
up on nowadays. So what we're looking for is a way to
reenact or you know reimagine this in the בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash,
mode. So it's not just saying it's like we offered a sacrifice.
First our whole preparation is like we've built the altar. We've bound
it up, we've created, we've built the altar and now we're shaking
it like we would wave, you know, the שתי הלחם shtei halechem
and now we're offering it. Okay? And that's I think very important
because also remember the whole idea of זכר למקדש, zeicher lemikdash, right?
I mean here we're talking about how they would do all these
rituals in the בית המקדש, Beis Hamikdash. we talked about לולב זכר
למקדש, lulav zeicher lemikdash, so it's like a very powerful גמרא Gemara
that's trying to create that virtual מקדש Mikdash reality now that we're
bringing this. Okay? אמר רבי ירמיה משום רבי שמעון בן יוחאי, Amar
Rabbi Yermiyah mishum Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai, and said רבי ירמיה Rabbi
Yermiyah in the name of רבי שמעון בן יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon ben
Yochai, ורבי יוחנן משום רבי שמעון המחוזי, veRabbi Yochanan mishum Rabbi Shimon
Hamachuzi, משום רבי יוחנן המכותי, mishum Rabbi Yochanan Hamakuti, interesting. כל העושה
איסור לחג, Kol ha'oseh issur lachag, anybody that does a binding to
the holiday, באכילה ובשתיה, ba'achila uveshtia, in eating and drinking, מעלה עליו
הכתוב כאילו בנה מזבח והקריב עליו קרבן, ma'aleh alav hakatuv k'ilu bana
mizbe'ach vehikriv alav korban, is like you built an altar and offered
a sacrifice, שנאמר, shene'emar, אסרו חג בעבותים, Isru chag ba'avotim, bind the
holiday with עבותים, avotim, right? He says here עבות, avot, means like
a, it's like a big animal, a thick animal, like עבות avot
means like thick, like a nice juicy animal, עד קרנות המזבח, ad
kornot hamizbe'ach, on the, on the altar. So you're binding your eating.
Now what does binding your eating mean? So רש"י Rashi says two
explanations. One just means that you have nice eating on the יום
טוב yom tov for שמחת יום טוב, simchas yom tov, okay, then
doesn't exactly explain what the word to bind means. The other explanation
is the famous day for what's, what do we call the day
after יום טוב? yom tov? אסרו חג. Isru Chag. To bind it
means to like add something onto it, connect to it the following
day and have the joy of the following day. Which is a
nice idea, but it doesn't exactly explain why that's like offering up
a sacrifice. What does the idea of אסרו חג, Isru Chag, I
mean that's where we get the word from, but how is it
connected to this idea of a sacrifice? So the מהרש"א Maharsha has
the third explanation which is very beautiful and which fits with the
word איסור. issur. The word איסור issur means to forbid, right? or
to hold yourself back, to constrain, to bind. And what the מהרש"א
Maharsha says is if you don't make yourself a glutton on יום
טוב, yom tov, you hold yourself back a little bit and therefore
you demonstrate that what your eating is a religious eating, it's to
enjoy the יום טוב, yom tov, it's to sort of, you know,
have שמחת החג, simchas hachag, but you don't let yourself like overly
indulge and fret and get caught up in your own satisfying of
your own like, you know, purely about satisfying your own appetite. So
then it's like you've offered it up, and there he says that
ties into the idea that we say that nowadays our table is
like an altar, right? That's an idea you've heard. So you will
make your יום טוב yom tov table into an altar and offer
a sacrifice on it, how? And this is a very interesting idea.
What do we mean when we say our table is an altar?
What does that even mean? So one way obviously of explaining it
is in the past the altar would eat the sacrifices as it
were and that would be our way of offering to God. Nowadays
if we do our eating with the recognition of God and in
a religious context, our eating is like the eating of the altar
and that's a way in which we serve God if we can
make it into a religious context. But what the מהרש"א Maharsha says
here is that if you actually hold yourself back, that's even more
resonates in the idea of sacrifice. You're not just taking it for
you. What's sacrifice? You're giving something of your own to God. So
here you're holding yourself back from eating this thing in front of
you, right? and you're offering it up as it were to God
in acknowledgment that this is not just about me indulging. Now again,
it doesn't say you should be ascetic on יום טוב. yom tov.
Obviously you should be eating and enjoying, but don't overly indulge, there
should be a degree of holding back. Beautiful. Yeah. And that's an
offering to God, and that makes it like you have build your
altar, you've made your table into your altar and offered up to
God. So very again, very beautiful powerful idea from the מהרש"א. Maharsha.
So and that again is interesting how we are trying to bring
the מקדש Mikdash reality, so much of this דף daf and these
few דפים dapim are about מקדש into our current reality. Okay, so
now the גמרא Gemara, continues. אמר חזקיה אמר רבי ירמיה משום רבי
שמעון בר יוחאי. Amar Chizkiyah amar Rabbi Yermiyah mishum Rabbi Shimon bar
Yochai. כל מצות כולן אין אדם יוצא בהן. Kol mitzvos kulan ein
adam yotzei bahen.
Since we mentioned רבי שמעון בר יוחאי, Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, right?
רבי ירמיה Rabbi Yermiyah in the name of רבי שמעון בר יוחאי,
Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai, we're doing a similar tradition and this obviously
also connects very much to סוכות. כל מצות כולן אין אדם יוצא
בהן אלא דרך גדילתן. Kol mitzvos kulan ein adam yotzei bahen ela
derech gdilasan. You don't fulfill your מצות mitzvos by you have to
use things that like grow unless you use them in the way
they grew. שנאמר shene'emar the verse says, עצי שטים עמדים, atzei shittim
omdim,
standing acacia wood. So meaning and therefore when it had to be
עומד, omed, it had to be standing the way it grows when
you use it in the משכן. mishkan. Again by the way notice
the connection to the משכן. mishkan. תניא נמי הכי, Tanya nami hachi,
עצי שטים עמדים שעומדים דרך גדילתן. atzei shittim omdim she'omdim derech gdilasan.
They stand, they have to be erected the way they grow. And
this is used to say why you're not יוצא yotzei לולב ואתרוג
lulav ve'esrog when they grow in the wrong direction. But again notice
the associations that are being created in the גמרא, Gemara right? The
גמרא Gemara is basically saying, you know, again bringing the מצוה mitzvah
of לולב ואתרוג lulav ve'esrog into the משכן. mishkan. Not only is
it bringing it into the משכן. mishkan. But the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
before made this bold statement: it's like you've built an altar. So
think what it's doing right now: it's connecting taking of the לולב
lulav *Lulav* and אתרוג esrog, *Esrog* to the building of the משכן
*Mishkan*, right? Not just to some ritual, but reminding us about the
whole משכן *Mishkan* was built by things that grow and using them
in the way they grow, and we also, when we take לולב
lulav *Lulav* and אתרוג *Esrog*, we have to use it in the
way that they grow. So it's very much again reinforcing this, bringing
us into this משכן *Mishkan* reality. By the way, it is interesting
though, if you think about it, an אתרוג *Esrog*, anybody ever see
an אתרוג *Esrog* grow on a tree? Does the פיטם *pitom* grow
up or down? So when the fruit hangs from the tree, the
פיטם *pitom* hangs down. So how come we take it up? So
the basic answer is because when it starts growing, it starts growing
up, but then the weight of it pulls it down. But that's
actually interesting about this based on this הלכה *halachah*. Okay, so now
the גמרא Gemara *Gemara* says like this: דבר אחר *davar acher*,
another explanation of עצי שטים עמדים *atzei shittim omdim*, עמדים *omdim* they
stand שמעמידים את ציפויין *shema'amidim es tzipuyan*. They hold their
coat, they're coated with gold, so it sort of doesn't like you
support the gold you know, they completely support the gold that coats
them. דבר אחר *davar acher*, which is not so clear what the
larger point about that is: עמדים *omdim* they stand שמא תאמר *shema
tomar*, this is a very famous גמרא Gemara *Gemara*, אבד סיברם ובטל
סיכוים *avad sivram u'vitel sikuyam*, lest you say that their hope is
lost and their again aspirations are nullified, meaning now we don't have
a בית המקדש Beis Hamikdash *Beis Hamikdash*, so that's it, it's all
a waste, it's never coming back, the end; lest you say that,
תלמוד לומר *talmud lomar* עצי שטים עמדים *atzei shittim omdim*, no, they're
standing, שעומדים לעולם ולעולמי עולמים *she'omdim l'olam u'l'olmei
olamim*, they're always eternally standing. Ultimately there will be a future בית
המקדש *Beis Hamikdash*, the hope is not lost. Maybe it also means
in a metaphysical way, they're continuing to stand even till today. So
again, notice how that reinforces the theme here as well. Here we
are post חורבן *horban*, but the point is don't worry, we still
are living, the בית המקדש *Beis Hamikdash* always exists. It'll come back
in the future, it exists even now. You can build your own
מזבח *mizbe'ach* and offer a sacrifice by taking the לולב *Lulav*. You
can do it by eating on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, right? So
all of this is creating that מקדש *mikdash* reality right now in
the context of סוכות *Sukkos*. Okay, ואמר חזקיה אמר רבי ירמיה *v'amar
Chizkiyah amar Rabbi Yirmiyah*, חזקיה *Chizkiyah* also says in
the name of רבי ירמיה *Rabbi Yirmiyah*, משום רבי שמעון Rabbi Shimon
בר bar יוחאי *mishum Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai*, so it's a same
trident of tradition here, trident of tradition. יכול אני לפטור את כל
העולם כולו מן הדין *yachol ani liftur es kol ha'olam kulo min
hadin*, this doesn't directly connect to what we were talking about, I
could exempt the entire world מן הדין *min hadin* from the divine
judgment from negative divine judgment, מיום שנבראתי ועד עתה *miyom shenivresi v'ad
atah*, from the day I was created until now, meaning I am
so righteous
that my merits would get everybody else off the hook
for all the bad deeds that were done from the day I
was created until now. ואלמלא אלעזר Elazar בני עמי *v'ilmalei Elazar bni
imi*, and if אלעזר Elazar, *Elazar* my son was together with me,
you remember רבי שמעון בר bar? יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai* and
אלעזר *Elazar* were the ones that went into the cave, מיום שנברא
העולם ועד עכשיו *miyom shenivra ha'olam v'ad achshav*, we could exempt the
world from all negative judgments from the day the world was created
until now. ואלמלא יותם בן עוזיהו עמנו *v'ilmalei Yotham ben Uzziah imanu*,
and if יותם בן עוזיהו *Yotham ben Uzziah*, a very righteous king,
was with us, מיום שנברא העולם ועד סופו *miyom shenivra ha'olam v'ad
sofo*, from the day the world was created until the very end
of creation. Okay, so again, not exactly clear what point he's trying
to make here and why this is an appropriate thing to say,
but we don't have time to figure that out or unpack it,
but it's quite a bold statement. ואמר חזקיה אמר רבי ירמיה משום
רבי שמעון בר bar יוחאי *v'amar Chizkiyah amar Rabbi Yirmiyah mishum Rabbi
Shimon bar Yochai*, a similar statement in the name of רבי שמעון
בר bar יוחאי *Rabbi Shimon bar Yochai*: ראיתי בני עליה *ra'isi bnei
aliyah*, I've seen those literally children of elevation, meaning righteous people, והן
מועטין *v'hein mu'atin*, and they're very few really righteous people in this
world. But here's what you should know: אם אלף הן *im elef
hein*, if the total number of righteous people are a thousand, then
אני ובני מהן *ani u'vni meihen*, I and my son are amongst
even the top thousand. אם מאה הן *im me'ah hein*, if there's
only a hundred real righteous people in this world, אני ובני מהן
*ani u'vni meihen*, I and my son are in the list. אם
שנים הן *im shnayim hein*, and by the way, even if there
were only two, guess who they are? אני ובני הן *ani u'vni
hein*, it's me and my son. Okay, so again, I really don't
know the larger point being made here. So the גמרא Gemara *Gemara*
says like this: ומי זוטרי כולי האי *u'mi zutrei kulei hai*, is
it really so small this list? Maybe it's only two? Maybe it's
only a hundred or a thousand? ואמר רבא *v'amar Rava*, and רבא
*Rava* says תמני סרי אלפי *temanei srei alfei*, eighteen thousand people is
דרא דהוי קמיה קודשא בריך הוא *dara d'havei kamei Kudsha Brich Hu*,
is the row in front of God, the row of like students
in God's ישיבה *yeshivah*, the row of people that surround God, but
there are eighteen thousand in God's what we would say innermost circle.
So it's not more than two or a hundred or a thousand.
שנאמר shenemar, *shene'emar*, the verse says: סביב שמונה עשר אלף *saviv shmonah
asar elef*, eighteen thousand, and that's being read it's the verse is
in יחזקאל *Yehezkel*, it's about the future Jerusalem, but it's being
read... See, so if you're looking through a an unlit lens, a
cloudy lens, then you are then there
are like 18,000, but the real innermost circle is only maybe a
thousand or a hundred or whatever. Okay. Wow. Well the
גמרא Gemara says comparing רבי שמעון to משה. Moses. Well okay
so that's a good pick up. So the מהרש"א Maharsha says what
does it mean that there's a thousand or a hundred that see
in in an in a lit lens, the גמרא Gemara says only
משה Moshe saw in in an in a lit lens. So the
מהרש"א Maharsha makes another bold statement and he says that's the גמרא
Gemara comparing משה Moshe to the prophets, but here we're talking not
about prophecy, but about being a sage. And being a sage is
greater than being a prophet. So that actually the sages can actually
be a thousand or a hundred. So it's also a pretty bold
statement, which means that pe- you know, that that yes, it's true,
sages could be on an equal level to משה. Moshe. You would
also assume it means as a- as a whatever you know, different
different type of way of inv- of visioning God or- or experiencing
God. Okay, so now the גמרא Gemara says like this, מי זוטר
כולי האי? mi zutra kulei hai? מסתכלי באספקלריא המאירה mistaklei b'aspaklaria hameira
מי זוטר כולי
האי? mi zutra kulei hai? גמרא's still not satisfied. Even those that
see in the lit lens, is it really so small, only a
thousand or a hundred? ואמר אביי, va'amar Abaye,
I'm sorry, only two. We're only going on the last part of
the statement when he suggested that there were only two people that
were really at the hi- you know, you know, that were the
real צדיקים. tzaddikim. Is it possible that even those that see in
the lit lens are really- it's possible it's just two? ואמר אביי,
v'amar Abaye, אביי Abaye says לא פחת עלמא מתלתין ושיתא צדיקי, lo
pachat alma mitlatim v'shita tzadikei, there's no fewer than 36 righteous- here's
the basis of the idea of the למד ווניקס- Lamed Vavniks there's
no fewer than 36 righteous people דמקבלי אפי שכינה בכל יומא d'mikablei
apei shechina b'chol yoma that greet God on a daily basis, meaning
that are directly in God's innermost circle. 36 is the minimum, not
two. שנאמר, shenemar, as the verse says, אשרי כל חוכי לו, ashrei
kol chochei lo, praise are all that wait for him. לו lo
בגימטריא, b'gematria, and לו lo in גימטריא gematria is 36. תלתין ושיתא
הוי. tlatim v'shita havei.
So how can you say it's just two? So the גמרא says
לא קשיא, lo kashya, it's not difficult. הא דעיילי בבר, ha d'aily
b'bar, those that go in בבר b'bar are two, הא דעיילי בלא
בר, ha d'aily b'lo bar, going in without בר bar is 36.
Now what's בר? bar So רש"י Rashi says בר means permission. If
you can just walk in to God's innermost chamber, obviously this is
all a metaphor based on you know a kingly court, but if
you could just walk in without permission, then it's possibly only two
and we'd be רבי שמעון בן יוחאי Rabbi Shimon ben Yochai and
אלעזר his son. Those that greet God every day but they need
permission, those are 36. Okay, that's what רש"י says. Others read the
word בר like בר normally means in Aramaic. What does בר mean?
Son. So he says no, those that go in with their sons,
that's just me and אלעזר, two. 36, there might be 36, but
that doesn't include their sons, that's just them. Those that are so
righteous and you know father and son teams, that's just the two
of us. Okay. Moving on, that was an interesting digression. בשעת פטירתן
מה הן אומרים? b'sha'as petirasan mah hen omrim? So now when they
would take leave of the altar and again the point that it's
very fascinating, the whole concept of taking leave, what would they say?
So, והא קא משתתף שם שמים ודבר אחר? v'ha ka mishtateif sheim
shamayim v'davar acher?
So they would say לך ולך מזבח, lach u'lach mizbei'ach, to God
and to you oh altar. So the גמרא says one minute, והא
קא משתתף שם שמים ודבר אחר, v'ha ka mishtateif sheim shamayim v'davar
acher, when in their words of praise they're combining God with the
altar, to God and to you oh altar. You don't- you don't
like combine God with anything, right? Like God and the altar are
on some equal level that you can you know- you know acknowledge
them in the same sentence? So the גמרא says ותניא, v'tanya, we
joined a ברייתא, baraita, כל המשתתף שם שמים ודבר אחר נעקר מן
העולם, kol hamishtateif sheim shamayim v'davar acher ne'ekar min ha'olam, if you
combine God's name with something else, meaning in like a word of
praise or in taking an oath- take an oath in the name
of God and heaven and earth- you're equating a created thing with
God. So you're uprooted from the world, it's heresy. שנאמר, בלתי לה'
לבדו, bilti laHashem levado, only to God alone, nothing else can be
combined with God. הכי קאמר, hachi ka'amar, this is what it means:
לך אנו מודים, l'ka anu modim,
to God we give thanks, ולך את המזבח אנו משבחים, v'lach at
hamizbei'ach anu m'shabchim, we give praise, or another way, לך אנו מודים,
l'ka anu modim, to God we give thanks, ולך to you the
altar אנו מקלסין, anu m'kalsin, again another word for praise. So when
it says לך ולך מזבח, lach u'lach mizbei'ach, it's like לך, Lecha
to God, to God is our fealty, like in an elliptical sentence,
and to you oh altar we praise, but not together. Okay. There's
a verb, an implicit verb between the לך and the לך מזבח.
Okay, so that's at least the way the גמרא is saying what
it meant, it means in תנא. Tanna. Question?
Yeah. Why would we even be praising an... that's something that humans...
So that's a good point. So רשי says the word מודים Modim
here is like we give thanks. We give thanks that there is
an altar as the altar, you know, is there to atone for
our sins in some... but nevertheless, to whom is the thanks directed?
You could say well thanks God for the altar. You don't thank
the altar. Yes, it is a anthropomorphism, you know, it
is you know we are treating the altar as a being to
which we are thanking, that is true. It's you know there's a
lot of very challenging, disturbing, you know anthropomorphic stuff going on here,
right? Like the אני והו הושיעה נא whatever that meant and you're
right direct addressing of the altar. It is, it's very you know
challenging ideas here. Okay, כמעשהו בחול, exactly what they were doing the
weekday they were doing שבת except they would gather the stuff beforehand.
So the גמרא says like this, אמר רב הונא מאי טעמא דרבי
יוחנן בן ברוקא, Amar Rav Huna mai taama deRabbi Yochanan ben Broka,
what's the reasoning of רבי יוחנן בן ברוקא Rabbi Yochanan ben Broka
who says that they would not use ערבות aravos but they would
use לולבים lulavim or maybe additionally use ערבות aravos but he would
focus on the לולבים? lulavim? So דכתיב dichtiv the verse says כפות,
kapot, it says the same way ערבי נחל arvei nachal the double
language told us that there was an ערבה ritual according to some,
the כפות kapot in the plural tells us that there's a לולב
ritual in the you know in the בית המקדש. אחת לולב ואחת
מזבח Achas lulav veachas mizbeach a special לולב ritual around the altar
in addition to the fact that there's generally a מצוה mitzva of
taking the לולב in the בית המקדש there was a particular ritual
around the altar. ורבנן אמרי Verabbanan amri and the רבנן Rabbanan would
say back כפת כתיב kapat ksiv it's written without the ו vav
so it's only one act. ולוי אמר כתמר, Velevi omer kitamar, לוי
Levi says no, it's not based on a verse, it's based on
the symbolism, okay? מה תמר זה Mah tamar zeh the same way
a palm tree אין לו אלא לב אחד ein lo ela lev
echad only has one heart. רשי says that it has something to
do with the way the marrow grows in the palm tree and
it's centralized like a human heart. Anyway, אף ישראל אין להם אלא
לב אחד לאביהם שבשמים. Af Yisrael ein lahem ela lev echad laavihem
shebashamayim.
So the palm tree is like the sense of single true but
anyway when you look at a palm tree the idea of like
a unity one because it grows so like so straight and so
tall right as opposed to other trees, right? So that symbolizes that
one heart one you know the idea of of like you know
feel of of like just all for one thing. So we're all
for God. The same as a palm tree is a single thing
all our heart is totally devoted to God. It also evokes that
statement about רבי עקיבא. Rebbe Akiva. Remember רבי עקיבא Rebbe Akiva said
one palm, one אתרוג, one הדס, hadas, one ערבה like it's all
about this you know fealty fidelity to God and that therefore because
that's symbolized by the by the palm tree we want to do
a ritual with the palm tree by the altar to show our
you know single worship of God. Let's read a little bit more.
So אף ישראל אין להם אלא... Af Yisrael ein lahem ela... אף
ישראל אין להם אלא לב אחד לאביהם שבשמים. Af Yisrael ein lahem
ela lev echad laavihem shebashamayim. We only have one heart to God.
אמר רב יהודה אמר שמואל... Amar Rav Yehuda amashmu... Okay then that's
it. So we will end with this today and tomorrow we'll pick
up on the halakhic discussions of making the very important making the
ברכה bracha of לולב and סוכה. sukkah. You had one final question
Charlie?
Is it תמר Tamar specifically the date palm? Yeah. Okay because there
are other palm trees that aren't like that.
Oh I see, yeah, but it is a date palm. Okay very
good.